[upbeat music playing]
[car engine revving]
[Jerry] Okay, okay,
this is my kind of car.
This is a 1979 Porsche 930 Turbo
in cashmere beige with a cork interior.
It has a flat-6 3.3 liter engine
mounted at the extreme rear of the car,
the worst possible place
for the most possible fun.
It has a KKK Turbo,
no relation to the racist
Southern Ku Klux Klan organization,
giving it 265 horsepower.
It has a four-speed manual gearbox.
It has cross-drilled,
ventilated disk brakes.
It goes 162 miles an hour.
This is a technical car for technical guys
who like technical things.
The word "guys" in this usage
is an all-inclusive term
for women, gays,
lesbians, and transgenders.
[upbeat music playing]
I love the color, I love the fenders,
I love the stance,
I love the accordion rubber bumpers,
the upright cooling fan, the big tach,
and the five-spoke Fuchs mag wheels.
My very special guest today is
my dear old friend, Mr. Garry Shandling.
Garry was one of the first comedian
friends of mine in LA to get a 9-11.
We have been very good friends
for a very long time,
and our careers have pretty much
paralleled most of that time.
We started at The Comedy Store in LA
at the same time.
We did The Tonight Show
with Johnny Carson at the same time.
We did our TV series in the '90s
at the same lot, at the same time,
right across the street from each other.
We were a pair,
like 9-11s and Southern California.
[phone ringing]
-[Jerry] Garry.
-[Garry] Oh, Jerry!
When do we do the phone call
that would be on air?
[Jerry] Now. We're doing it now.
[Garry] Oh, my God. I haven't talked to
you in so long, I can't wait to see you.
Maybe you had it right, because everything
in my life needs to be edited.
[Jerry] Well, everything in your life
comes after a 19 second pause.
[Garry] I don't know why you say that.
[both laughing]
I'm Jerry Seinfeld, and this is
Comedians in Cars Getting Coffee.
-I love you.
-Love you, too.
[upbeat music playing]
Would you ever go into a tanning salon?
[Garry] Not without sunblock on.
If they open a store,
I feel like I should go in.
I think, "Oh, Burger Lounge.
Oh, I should go there and get a burger.
They've gone to all the trouble
of opening that place up."
I find you incredibly intelligent,
except for that idea,
because you'd be busy all day.
You would have nothing left in your life.
-If we stopped everywhere...
-I would!
...we'd have no show.
[Garry] The Matthew McConaughey
commercials for Lincoln,
they could use a comedian
in the passenger seat.
You should be in the passenger seat
looking at Matthew McConaughey.
-Right.
-Saying, "Huh?
I don't know what you're talking about.
Are you trying to sell this car
to people who mumble?
Do you want to sell it to people
who just kind of stumble in and go,
'Hey, you know, I'm looking
for something like a Lincoln.'"
What is this? People driving around
by themselves just smirking.
Who the hell goes from an Oscar
right to a car commercial?
That's why you need to be
in the seat next to him.
That would be a great commercial.
You be Matthew McConaughey,
and I'll be you.
[down-tempo music playing]
You just gotta drive.
-It's Jerry. Oh, my God.
-[laughing]
I'm stuck in the car
with Matthew McConaughey.
Did you find my jacket?
Did you find the leather jacket?
Hold on one second.
I never thought about driving Lincolns,
I just drove them.
It was a smart car, I just...
This is so weird, he's not on the phone,
he's not talking to anybody, just listen.
You got a straight flush, straight flush.
[upbeat music playing]
-This is where Beatty lives, right?
-Yeah.
Now it's suddenly turned into a star tour?
So, it turns out I had
a hyperparathyroid gland
that was undiagnosed,
because the symptoms mirrored
the exact same symptoms
an older Jewish man would have.
Which is, you know, lethargic,
you get puffy, you get heavy.
You kind of feel like you want a divorce,
even though you're not married.
You know, I was an electrical engineering
major at the University of Arizona,
and that taught me the discipline
of working out formulas
and having no other life,
because you had to work so hard
to get that stuff right.
But of course that was not as difficult
as writing comedy.
No, because there's ultimately
an answer to an equation.
There's an answer to a joke.
Well, I don't think
Einstein bounced it off a crowd.
What do you think of this?
A plus C equals D-squared. No?
-Yeah.
-That doesn't seem to get anything.
[upbeat jazz music playing]
[Garry] There was a time
when I was writing for Sanford and Son,
and then walked into the Comedy Store,
and there you were doing standup.
Then I was just starting amateur night.
Mitzi wouldn't give me any spots, really.
[Jerry] I worked at the Improv
because she disliked me.
She just instinctively disliked me.
Well, I can understand that.
I mean, really?
[laughing]
-You and I were the two guys...
-Right.
...who kind of had the notes, went in,
did the work, and left.
And all that [bleep] that went on,
which we'll talk about when we get there,
because you'll still be able
to smell puke from 1978.
[Garry] I'm not getting out. It's always
tough for me at The Comedy Store.
-There's a vibe that never changes.
-Never. It's horrible.
But let's deal with it, come on.
This is a little uncomfortable for me.
But Garry,
this was the kingdom and the power.
In the '70s and '80s,
this was the place you had to come to
if you wanted to be a real comedian.
[Jerry] Did you ever see actual cocaine
or heroin at the Comedy Store?
-[Garry] I did not.
-I didn't either,
and we knew it was all around us.
But Garry,
I used to stand here and watch you.
[Garry] This really is a killer.
I go up on stage, and Jim McCawley from
The Tonight Show is standing back here.
And he was the guardian of the gate.
So, Jim McCawley says to me
"That was so good. How's next Tuesday
for you on The Tonight Show?"
-And that's what changed my life.
-Wow.
[pleasant jazz music playing]
[Garry] It's like every other person
has passed away.
[Jerry] Either personally
or professionally passed away.
[Garry] That's right.
[laughing]
[inaudible]
You know what, Garry?
This is still a really good comedy room.
I would love to go up and work out here.
And it's not just that we have
all the history here, this is a good room.
You can feel it. Certain rooms
don't have it. This room has it.
[brisk jazz music playing]
So, I'm on stage once. You know,
I'm talking and working on stuff,
and it's going fine, and I see movement.
Out of the corner of my eye,
I see movement right over here.
And I look down,
and a new waitress has got her tray,
and she's come up this way onto the stage
to serve these two tables,
and I'm actually standing there like this.
I'm not mad,
I just can't believe what I'm seeing.
So, people say, "Wow, do you get nervous
when you go on TV?"
They don't understand
the [bleep] we've seen.
One night, I was here,
and it must have been 1:00 in the morning,
and the guy was sitting right there.
And there were no...
There was nobody else here,
and I just started up on him.
[laughing]
But here's what happened.
I said, "You know what? I feel so bad.
I always pick on the person
that's in front of the mic, so just move."
So, he was a nice guy,
and he got up and he moved over there.
And I picked up the mic and I put it here,
and I started up on him again.
[both laughing]
[slow jazz music playing]
It still has its vibe.
I mean, I didn't really know how to be.
-I was a guy from Arizona that came--
-[Jerry] So what?
Nobody gives a [bleep] where you're from.
Yeah, I'm sorry I brought that up.
-Another big Garry shot. Look at that one.
-This picture's totally embarrassing.
-You look so handsome.
-Where's your picture?
Don't know, I didn't see it.
Just skipping it
because you don't want to--
I didn't see it. I looked for it,
I didn't see it.
I'm really okay. I'm okay with it.
[inaudible]
What's that doing up there?
[Garry] I think that's if you're laying
flat in the parking lot,
and you think your life is over,
you look up and you go, "Wait,
there's another workshop I could go to."
[upbeat jazz music playing]
[Jerry] You know, David Brenner
passed away last year.
Do you ever think about,
like, all that material?
I'm sorry.
So, I'm at a stage in my life
where I actually care about the person.
Here's what I thought you were gonna say.
"Did you ever realize
when David Brenner died,
and Robin,
the actual impermanence of life?"
I never thought,
"God, there goes a lot of material."
-That's hilarious that you think that way.
-[Jerry] Well, that was the hard part.
Anyone can just pop out and live,
that's easy.
Gee, all that material,
he worked so hard on it.
It's just gone. It doesn't mean anything
to anyone anymore.
I mean, it took so much work to create it.
That material, and your material,
is purely a vehicle for you
to express your spirit.
And your soul and your being, and that's
why you're fantastic, so you keep...
So it doesn't have any value beyond that?
It doesn't have any value
beyond you expressing yourself spiritually
in a very soulful, spiritual way.
It's why you're on the planet.
God, open up the sunroof.
What year is this?
So, when you saw Robin Williams
the first time,
you don't remember everything he said,
it was just that, his presence.
[slow jazz music playing]
May Robin rest in peace.
I'm sure, like me, you were stunned.
-I don't know how you felt.
-Yeah. Mmm-hmm.
I was sitting there watching CNN anyway,
and they broke in and said,
"Robin Williams killed himself."
I sat there, and I was frozen.
This is totally true,
and I was in that kitchen of mine.
Then Wolf Blitzer says, "63 is so young."
And then I looked up with a little hope,
because I'm about the same age
as Robin, all right?
Then I realized "63 is so young"
is a phrase you never hear
relative to anything but death.
-Right.
-"Sixty-three is so young
to be playing in the NFL."
You don't... Nothing.
You have to die in your 60s for them
to say, "Boy, he was young."
[cheerful music playing]
I forgot to ask her for coffee right away.
Are you in the mood for coffee?
Yeah, I can do more coffee.
[Jerry] In the old days, you and I,
we were both handling
these very challenging jobs that we had.
I ran into somebody
whose name I can't recall.
Some comedian who had
a 12-show commitment.
I said, "How's it going?" He said,
"This is so much easier than I thought.
I'm having so much fun." And I thought...
-Oh, my God.
-Oh, my God. He's in trouble.
-And then, of course, he was out.
-He's out.
But, in any case, we're really connecting
four layers below this cup of coffee.
Yes.
This is part of the key
of our relationship.
Because when I say,
"It's a [bleep] minefield,"
they go, "Shandling's complaining."
You know, I listen to the blues,
it's the exact same words I say,
and people go, "This is fantastic."
But when I say, "My baby left me,"
they go, "Stop complaining."
[slow jazz music playing]
I noticed that I go through
a reflective period,
and think about either some relationship
I might have been in at the time,
or my exploits at the Carlisle.
You have exploits?
I can't believe you have exploits.
-What? Come on.
-Nothing.
-I can't, I can't right now. I just can't.
-All right.
Suit yourself.
There's a little attitude
when you say "Suit yourself" there.
I like to say "Suit yourself"
because nobody says that anymore.
I like "Go [bleep] yourself."
[both laugh]
-Why?
-I don't know.
That's another expression that just...
There's no image
even that it takes you to.
I don't know
why that line became so popular.
-Which?
-"Go [bleep] yourself."
That's the way I actually initiate sex.
[both laughing]
That's my opening.
[jazz music playing]
[Jerry] So, when you did Larry Sanders,
which besides being
one of my favorite sitcoms of all time,
you invented a certain kind of air on TV
that had never existed before.
There's a certain kind of air
on I Love Lucy,
there's a certain kind of air
on Mary Tyler Moore.
You created an original content form.
Do you ever watch TV,
The Office, Modern Family,
and go, "Oh, look, they're still doing me.
Still doing that thing I invented."
I knew when I explained to HBO
what I wanted to do,
I couldn't say, "It's a little bit
of this, a little bit of that."
I couldn't even do that.
And I mean, they thought I was crazy.
I said, "This doesn't even exist.
The world doesn't even exist.
What are you doing?"
-Who would you say this to?
-To other homeless people.
[jazz music playing]
About eight months ago,
I'm home sick, I was sick.
When a Jew doesn't feel well,
he cannot repeat it too many times.
Even the Buddhist part of me
was saying, "You're sick."
Melissa Rivers had a memorial for her mom,
-and I was not well.
-I understand.
So, I got home at, like, 10:30 p.m.,
and I was exhausted.
I'd just gone through that,
and I'm taking my suit off
like those scenes where you see
someone's taking their clothes off
leading to a sexual scene,
except it's just menswear.
It's just my clothing.
I get into bed and I'm exhausted,
because I was not feeling well,
and I'm exhausted.
Yeah, you mentioned that.
And I get in bed, and it's going on 11:30,
and on Jimmy Fallon...
they announce Jeffrey Tambor
is on Jimmy Fallon.
So I go, "I gotta stay up and watch this."
And I'm watching it,
and I'm not feeling well.
You mentioned that.
And then Jimmy says to Jeffrey,
"How's Garry?"
And he said,
"He's probably watching right now."
And they turned to the camera,
and they go, "Hi, Garry."
And I'm sitting there, like this.
"Hey, Garry, how you doing?"
It was like, "Hope you're feeling okay."
I mean, they don't know I'm sick
or anything. It startled me.
I was a little close to the TV.
And so I wrote Jimmy a note that just
said, "Please, don't ever do that again."
[laughing]
What I want at my funeral is an actual
boxing referee to do a count,
and at five, just wave it off and say,
"He's not getting up."
[both laughing]
[pleasant jazz music playing]
[inaudible]
-Did you use to come out here...
-No, I never walked.
-...and go to restaurants?
-No, the trouble is,
I was so busy. I remember going out to eat
once with a guest who was on the show,
and when I got back 30 minutes later,
our producer was standing
in my parking spot like this.
And, you know, I'm gonna say this now.
It was my show.
-Right.
-Can I just have one lunch?
-You want me to answer that question? No.
-Yes. Yeah.
-Get your ass back in the office.
-Yeah.
Nobody wants to hear your whining
about having your own show...
-All the money you've made...
-[Garry] Right.
[Jerry] Nobody likes to hear rich, famous
people whining about how hard it was.
[Garry] Well, then we sure don't have
a presidential candidate, do we?
-[Jerry] How you doing?
-[guard] All right, you?
I'm with Garry Shandling.
We used to work here.
-Really? Vaguely.
-Do you remember us?
This is those parking spots
for your offices.
Yeah, we were in here.
[Jerry] I remember one of my writers
told me they talked
to one of your writers,
and they said
that they came to your house,
and that you would float in the pool,
and they'd be pitching.
If you said to me, I was face down
in the pool, I'd say, "That's possible."
[gentle jazz music playing]
[Jerry] This is the walk that we would do.
Many times we would call each other.
We'd say, "Got a minute?"
And we would walk
and hear each other's issues.
In fact, I've said,
"Thank God I could speak to Jerry."
Here's your New York street.
[Jerry] Yeah, this street
was built for me and my show.
[both] Wow!
[Garry laughing]
Whoo.
I have not been here in many years.
[inaudible]
[gentle jazz music playing]
-I got two jokes in one episode.
-[Jerry] Yeah, you did.
It was the one where George took the book
at the bookstore into the bathroom.
That's right.
George says to me, "Well, don't you
read when you go in the bathroom?"
And I go, "No, George, I don't.
I just use the bathroom."
And George's line was,
"Well, aren't you something?"
That was your line.
[Jerry whispers] The script girl walk.
The brisk, high-energy script girl walk.
It's another world, isn't it?
Another time?
-Yeah.
-[Garry] What is your feeling?
Positive? Do you miss it?
[Jerry whispers] Do you remember
when you were a kid,
and you were going to the bathroom
at school, and you could pee so far?
You could just, you would step back
further and further
and you could pee, like, 12 feet.
It's like that.
-[Jerry chuckling]
-I didn't know how to put it.
[Garry] This feels like it's almost...
It's not your set,
but it's the same dimension.
[Jerry] Yes, it is, it's very similar.
I bet you we could still do a sitcom.
All you need is an awkward situation.
[upbeat jazz music playing]
[whispering] What did you do,
did you drink everything?
[scoffs, whispers]
Now what am I gonna do?
We can't both go out with her.
If you asked her out and I asked her out.
Now I'm gonna have to go out to eat.
What if I go out with her,
then I pretend I'm sick,
I'll leave in the middle of the date
and then you show up.
She'll never notice the difference.
You know, she isn't that smart.
It's been really on my mind
to talk you about that.
Thanks.
[Jerry, softly] We used to run this town.
[upbeat music playing]
[Garry] Remember, there was a blind
comedian named Gabriel something,
and I wrote him a joke about, he drives
with his hands out the car window,
because those little bumps
on the lines are actually Braille markers.
What makes that joke funny is that
it's not about a blind guy driving.
I wrote a suicide note once that said,
"I'm not mad at anyone. This is just
something I want to do for myself."
It's not funny, is it?
It's too close to the truth.
-Yeah.
[Jerry] So, being completely honest.
The shock of Robin Williams
committing suicide.
Were you completely surprised?
The news broadcasters were on TV saying
"Why would Robin Williams
want to kill himself?
He just finished doing a TV series,
he's got two movies in the can,
and he's scheduled to shoot another one.
Why would you kill yourself?"
And I was sitting there with somebody,
I said, "She just gave the reason."
[slow jazz music playing]
[Garry] So, one time I was
with the Dalai Lama and he said,
"I understand you have some joke
about the Buddha."
How would you like to be in this position?
"Your Holiness."
And you know, he's looking at me, he's got
the glasses on, he's the Dalai Lama.
I'm talking to the Dalai Lama.
And I'm comfortable with that.
And I said, "Well, Buddha never got
married because his wife would have said,
"'Are you gonna sit around
the house like that all day?'
'Well, I'm meditating, honey.'
'Why don't you meditate
while you're taking out the trash?'"
And there's dead silence
in this little hut,
except for the three American monks
who are laughing hysterically.
And so, then I explained to him the joke.
"In American culture,
the husbands and wives sometimes argue,
because the wife thinks
the husband is lazy and sitting around."
Now he goes, "Oh!
Funny."
That's what you want to do,
you want to have a three-minute gap
from when you tell the joke
to when you get the laugh.
[Jerry laughing]
You know, I went in to get a CT scan
last Wednesday.
And I go in there, and the guy says,
the tech guy,
"Hey, Garry Shandling, I'm a big fan."
He said, "I did a CT scan
a year ago of you."
He said, "Do you have cancer?"
I said, "No."
He said, "Good, you're still alive.
'Cause I was watching the news,
and it seems like if you had passed away
I would have heard about it on the news."
And I said, "Well, I don't know, man.
I mean, uh, I don't know if they would
have broken in or anything, but..."
I didn't know what to say to the guy.
He kept at it. And he said, "That's so
great that Garry Shandling is still alive.
Fantastic." But it was like...